<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fear of God: vvhat it is, and exhorted to as one of the great lessons God calls upon men to learn by his great dispensations in the last days. In a sermon preached unto the Church of Christ meeting in Petty France London, the tenth day of the sixth month. Anno 1656.  By the faithful servant of Christ John Pendarves a little before his death.</title>
            <author>Pendarves, John, 1622-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E907_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168446</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168446)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 137:E907[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fear of God: vvhat it is, and exhorted to as one of the great lessons God calls upon men to learn by his great dispensations in the last days. In a sermon preached unto the Church of Christ meeting in Petty France London, the tenth day of the sixth month. Anno 1656.  By the faithful servant of Christ John Pendarves a little before his death.</title>
                  <author>Pendarves, John, 1622-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.I. for Livewell Chapman, and are to be sold at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication is signed: John Cox.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fear of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168446:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Fear of God: VVhat it is, And EXHORTED TO As one of the Great Leſſons God calls upon men to learn by his great Diſpenſations in the laſt days.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon Preached unto the Church of Chriſt meeting in <hi>Petty France</hi> London, the Tenth day of the Sixth Month. <hi>Anno</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By that faithful Servant of Chriſt</hi> John Pendarves <hi>a little before his Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Crown in Popeſ-head Alley. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168446:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168446:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Church of God, WHICH He hath purchaſed with his own Bloud, meeting at ABINGDON</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Precious and Beloved:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon is eſpecially commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to your view, as being thoſe which I judge have moſt right unto it, becauſe of that near relation which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you and the Author of it, a taſte of whoſe ſavoury ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit you may here behold, near his Death, which you have often heard and ſeen in his
<pb facs="tcp:168446:3"/>
Life; it is doubtleſs a loſſe, yea a very great loſſe, as to <hi>Sion</hi> in general, ſo eſpecially to you in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, to have ſuch a painful Labourer taken out of the Vineyard, but I hope you have learned as in other things, ſo in this, to ſay,<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 21.14.</note> the Will of the Lord be done; this is our comfort, that God<note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 2.15.</note> hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the Spirit, and hee will never want Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to doe his work by; if he take away <hi>Moſes</hi> hee will raiſe up a<note n="c" place="margin">Joſh. 1.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and if he take away an <hi>Elijah,</hi> he will<note n="d" place="margin">2 King. 2.9:</note> double his Spirit upon ſome <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha;</hi> and who knows but God may take away ſuch tall Cedars, that ſome low Shrubs may grow up, and be active for God, in their generation. Surely, every ſuch Diſpenſation, as it is a ſpectacle of our Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo it loudly calls us to our duty to<note n="e" place="margin">Joh. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>work whiles it is day,</hi> that with <hi>Paul,</hi> wee may have<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 4 7.</note> fought our fight before we ſhall finiſh our courſe; and with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 13.36.</note> we may ſerve our generation, (by the Will of God) before we fall aſleep.</p>
            <p>As touching the Work it ſelf, which you are here preſented with, it treats concerning the fear of God, (a Subject) which I deſire may be as profitable, as it is ſeaſonable in this our day; wherein though Gods Judgements<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 26.9</note> have been abroad in the earth, yet the inhabitants of the World will not learn Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſa. 36.1</note> and the tranſgreſsions of the wicked doe plainly declare, that <hi>there is no fear of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes;</hi> and if wee look into the Lives of Profeſſors, we have cauſe to fear that there is but little of this filial fear to be found among them, which ſhould cauſe them to<note n="k" place="margin">Pſa. 4.4.</note> ſtand in awe, and not ſin; and too many there are that profeſs to fear God, that yet
<pb facs="tcp:168446:3"/>
fear not to ſin, againſt him; but how much ſoever, this being neglected, yet it appears to bee our duty, and that which God calls for from us, by vertue of his Supremacy over us: <hi>If I bee a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a maſter, where is my fear? ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Malachy <hi>1.6.</hi> but I ſhall not Expatiate upon this point, but referre you to the Diſcourſe it ſelf; for further information, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which the Reader is to bee further premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that this Sermon being not intended by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor for the Preſs, nor his Notes left behind him, neither being alive to correct it, it may want ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of that luſtre, which otherwiſe might have atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it; yet however, to ſatisfie the deſire of ſome god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Friends, as alſo for the general profit, it is here preſented to Publick view, as fully as it could be taken out of one Short-hand Copy, written from his mouth, and I deſire that the<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 33.16.</note> bleſsing of him that dwelt in the Buſh, may goe along with it; that the fear of God may hereby be wrought where it is not, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed where it is, that thoſe that fear not God, may be made to fear him, and thoſe that doe fear God, may fear him more, and more.</p>
            <p>And now (Dear Brethren) I ſhall leave it with you, as the words of your dying Paſtor, not doubting but it will be of weight upon your ſpirits, and ſome ſatisfaction to you, to read his Works, when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hear his words; this only I ſhall adde, as my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to you, and of you, that you would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read the words, but doe the works, that his words may be read in your works, and your Lives may bee as ſo many Volumes of his Labours;
<pb facs="tcp:168446:4"/>
that as on Earth you were his joy, ſo in Heaven you may bee his Crown; and as hee is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, you may follow after, and at laſt meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſit down together in the Kingdome of Glory; to which place, and portion, that you with my ſelf may have a ſafe Conduct, is the ardent deſire, and prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in our Head Chriſt, <hi>JOHN COX</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168446:4"/>
            <head>The Fear of God: Opened, and exhorted too, from <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. the former part of the fourth verſe. <hi>Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy name!</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I come to ſpeak more particularly to theſe words, I ſhall offer ſomething in a more general way in relation to this Book of the <hi>Revelations;</hi> which wee finde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended eſpecially, to the Churches of Chriſt, as you may ſee in Chap. 1. verſ. 11. <hi>What thou ſeeſt write in a Book, and ſend it to the ſeven Churches, &amp;c.</hi> You may take notice of the <hi>way,</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> wherein the Spirit of God walked in the diſcovery of Truth to the Saints under the Goſpel: and it is worthy your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how that firſt the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, being poured out upon the Apoſtles, did in the firſt place by them, inſtruct the people to whom they preached, touching thoſe <hi>foundation truthes</hi> (as I may ſo call them) which did eſpecially ſet forth Goſpel-faith; and you may obſerve, how the Wiſdome of God is very glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this <hi>way,</hi> and <hi>method,</hi> wherein the Lord did lead forth the Apoſtles, thoſe Primitive Preachers of the Goſpel, and thoſe that were under the conduct of the Apoſtles in their days.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord made known to them, the Doctrine
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168446:5"/>
of Grace, in order to their beleeving in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, They were inſtructed in the Doctrine of Baptiſme, and after this,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They were gathered into Church Order, to waite upon God for further diſcoveries of truth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, After God had by the Apoſtles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their days, ſet the Churches of Chriſt in order; then Jeſus Chriſt ſends this Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to them, and I finde it not given to them till then; and doubtleſs that confuſion that over-ſpread that part of the World called Chriſtendome, hath ſprung very much from thoſe that have preached truth, in that they did not firſt lay down thoſe foundations, truths of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though I would not aſcribe over much to order, yet you muſt know it is not without infinite wiſdome in God, which diſpenſeth his Truths in ſuch an order to the Sons of men.</p>
            <p>And though I would not hold you long (in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) yet I would ſpeak a little further to this, becauſe I ſee many in this day at a great loſs, for want of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the order of truth, that God hath layed down in his Word; ſome are very much troubled about Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, before they are really ſetled upon Jeſus Chriſt; and ſome are very much buſying themſelves about the matters of Worſhip, before they cloſe with Chriſt, the foundation; and ſo having not cloſed with Jeſus Chriſt, they build as men without a foundation; Others againe, when they come to be inſtructed in matters of Faith, are apt to minde other Ordinances that are further off, as <hi>Breaking of Bread;</hi> whereas the order of Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, is, that the very next thing after <hi>beleeving,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168446:5"/>
is, to be <hi>Baptized,</hi> in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; which perſons not obſerving, but miſſing the true way of God, they are toſſed to and fro, and know not where to fix, not taking notice of the due order: wherein the Lord lays down truth in his bleſſed Word.</p>
            <p>And poſſibly ſome (alſo) may be under the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of neglecting thoſe truthes, which concerne the foundation in matters of Faith, and Order (nay it is frequently ſo ſeen of many (of whom I deſire to ſpeak tenderly, ſuppoſing they do it weakly) that they are buſying themſelves in the underſtanding of the higheſt diſcoveries of God in this Book of the <hi>Revelations</hi>) and yet are not ſetled upon the foundation of the Goſpel, nor brought into the order of it; and therefore as to many that are ſoaring high in theſe things, I deſire they would conſider, whether they have not unadviſedly leaped over thoſe foundation truthes, which they ſhould have minded in their going on to thoſe <hi>glorious Truths,</hi> revealed in the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſay God is tied up to this order, but yet I ſay, this is the way, God would have his people waite upon him in; and God bringing his people out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> will (I doubt not) lead them, to obſerve truth in that order wherein it was laid down, in the firſt diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And (therefore) I being now to ſpeak unto a Church of Chriſt already planted in the Faith, and order of the Goſpel, I hope none will bee offended at my making choyce of a portion of Scripture in this Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> if any be, I may make my Apology from the eleventh verſe of the firſt Chapter, which holds forth unto us: that this Book, with the things therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, is ſent unto the Churches; <hi>I Jeſus have ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168446:6"/>
mine Angel to teſtifie theſe things in the Churches, and hee that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches;</hi> which you have ſeverall times repeated in the ſecond and third Chapters of this Book, ſo that you ſee, the things held forth in this Book, are ſuch as the Churches of Chriſt are ſpecially to hearken unto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt hath in a ſpecial manner commended theſe things to the Churches.</p>
            <p>And let me adde, that this Book hath a glorious bleſſing annexed to the reading and hearing of it, and the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things which are written therein, you have not ſuch a Bleſſing annexed to every Book as to this; and oh! that it were not the Sin of many Churches, that they are ſo backward in looking into the things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in this Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> when as God ſends it eſpecially, and particularly unto them.</p>
            <p>And indeed, I judge it is a matter of duty, eſpecially for the Angels, Meſſengers, and Paſtors of Churches, to be diligently ſearching into (in order to the finding out of) thoſe Truths that are written therein, and according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, to hold them forth to the Churches; for truly, I grieve to think how much Church-members are unacquainted with many things written therein, as what the Beaſt is, what is his Mark, and the Number of his Name, when as ſuch dreadful Judgements are pronounced againſt ſuch as worſhip the Beaſt, or his Image, or receive his Mark in their fore-heads, or in their hands; yet alas! how few Members in Churches are there, that labour to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in theſe things, ſurely hee that knows not of a danger, where it is, and how it lies: is in danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into it unawares.</p>
            <p>But to come to my Text, in this fifteenth Chapter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168446:6"/>
you read of a Victory obtained over the Beaſt, and not only ſo, but over his Image, Mark, and the number of his Name, by a Party ſtanding on the Sea of Glaſs, having the Harps of God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. their Song follows; and they ſang the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Servant of God, and the Song of the Lamb, ſaying, <hi>Great and marvellous are thy Works, Lord God Almighty, juſt and true are thy ways, thou King of Saints, who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I come to the words themſelves, I would in a general way lay down ſomething for your informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Context; that which I ſuppoſe will bee the great inquiry upon the view of this Scripture, is, what the Beaſt is, and who they are that get the victory over him, his Mark and Image? and therefore I ſhall briefly hint ſomething concerning this Beaſt, and the conquering Party that ſhall prevail over him.</p>
            <p>That which to me is the beſt help to diſcover the Beaſt, his Mark, and Image: eſpecially the Beaſt, what he is, are the ſeveral qualifications of thoſe which get the victory over him; you may partly know the Beaſt by his oppoſites, thoſe which rejoyce at the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming of him, now who they are that have had, and maintained a controverſie with this Beaſt, you may ſee deſcribed in the ſecond, third, and fourth verſes of this Chapter, and their frames, and qualifications may be judged, by ſeveral Characters given to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They are a People attained to ſome meaſure of purity, therefore ſet forth ſtanding upon a Sea of Glaſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They are a People bent to praiſe God for his great Works, they have the Harps of God, and they ſing, &amp;c. They are a people that dare not ſlight Gods great Works, if God bring them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> they have it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168446:7"/>
much upon their hearts, and they ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Song of the Lamb, like thoſe in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. and you know upon what account it was that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſang that Song, it was when Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> was brought out of <hi>Egypts</hi> bondage, and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> deſtroyed; whence it appears,</p>
            <p n="3">3 That theſe are a people ſeriouſly minding of, and much affected with Gods wonderful Works, in their deliverance from Spiritual <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cry out, <hi>Great and marvellous are thy Works, Lord God Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 They are a People that aſcribe all to God, and give him the praiſe of all his Works. I ſuppoſe all will grant, that the great Works God is to doe in the World, will be done by Inſtruments, yet this people doe not extoll man in this work, but cry out, <hi>Great and marvellous are THY Works, Lord God Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 They are a People that juſtifie God in all his Works, and ways, both of deliverance to his People, and judgement upon his enemies; which ſhews that they are ſuch as compare Gods Word, and his Works to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and have alſo been ſeriouſly exerciſed in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the ſins of the Enemy, that they thus juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God in his Judgements towards them, it being what they had deſerved, and hee had ſpoken, and therefore they cry out <hi>[Juſt and true] are thy ways.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="6">6 They acknowledge Chriſt to bee King of Saints, <hi>Thou King of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 They are a People truly fearing God, and ſtanding up for the glory of his Name, and this you have in the Text, <hi>Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy name?</hi> they are a people of ſerious ſpirits, truly fearing God, and ſuch as ſtand for the glory of God, and not their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168446:7"/>
own advantages in the world, but that God may have glory; this is that which they have moſt in their eye, and upon their hearts, that God may have a great Name in the world; <hi>Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy name?</hi> So that you ſee, thoſe which ſhall get the victory over the Beaſt, are not a People of a looſe and wanton converſation; I take Antichriſt his Power, and falſe Miniſtery, which have ſtood up in Chriſtendome, (ſo called) for many Generations, to be the Off-ſpring of thoſe, which <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpake of in their Epiſtles, which you have there deſcribed, but thoſe that ſhall get the victory over them are perſons of a contrary ſpirit— But againe</p>
            <p n="8">8 It appears they are a People of great Light, and much Faith in the Propheſies, concerning the coming in of the Nations to Worſhip God, and own Jeſus Chriſt, for this is a part of their Song, <hi>All Nations ſhall come and worſhip before thee, for thy Judgements are made manifeſt;</hi> they are not a narrow ſpirited People (which conteſt with the Beaſt) ſuch as only deſire that Chriſt ſhould bee exalted in the Nations, Cities, or places wherein they live, or in their own Church, but through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the earth; ſo zealous are they for the honour of Chriſt above their own private, and perſonal intereſts: Theſe are their qualifications.</p>
            <p>And therefore if you conſider where theſe qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are moſt to be found, and who they are that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, it may help you to finde out the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> in his moſt <hi>Refined Habit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to that part of the Song that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to ſpeak unto, in theſe words, <hi>Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168446:8"/>Two things there are which are very much upon the heart of this People, that get victory over the Beaſt; the</p>
            <p>Firſt is, to <hi>Fear the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To <hi>exalt the greatneſs of his name,</hi> and this upon the account of his Judgements being made manifeſt; ſo that the obſervation I ſhall give you from the words is this:</p>
            <p>Obſ. <hi>That the two great Leſſons that God calls upon men to learn by his great Diſpenſations in the laſt days, when hee brings his Judgements upon the wicked, is, to fear God, and give glory to his name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may be concluded from this holy Expoſtulation of theirs, in their Spiritual rejoycing, this they had learned themſelves, and this they rejoyce in, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould learn to <hi>fear God, and give glory to his name;</hi> ſo that I ſay, theſe are the two Leſſons God would learn the Sons of men, when he is bringing Judgements upon his enemies, namely, to fear him, and glorifie his name.</p>
            <p>That this is ſo, you may ſee clearly in <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.6, 7. <hi>And I ſaw another Angel fly in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpel to preach to them that dwell upon the earth, and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People, ſaying, Fear God, and give glory to him.</hi> (Why ſo) <hi>for the hour of his Judgement is come;</hi> ſo that you ſee theſe are the two great Leſſons that God calls upon men to learn, when his Judgements are going forth in the earth; as if (indeed) in theſe two things were ſummed up the whole duty of man in the laſt days.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall briefly lay before you ſome things further to clear this truth, that theſe are the two Leſſons God calls men to learn, from the Diſpenſation of his great Works in the laſt days; and it may further appear upon this ground.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:168446:8"/>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe theſe are the two Leſſons, which being learned, doe very much ſerve to fit and prepare men for thoſe great deſignes which God hath to bring to paſs in the laſt days; now, thoſe qualifications God eſpecially looks after, and requires of the Sons of men, (at any time and ſeaſon) which may beſt fit them for the Work God hath to doe at ſuch a ſeaſon: Now, what qualifications are there that more fitly ſerve for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of Gods great Works, than to fear God, and have reſpect unto his name?</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the fear of God, you ſhall finde, when God had any Work to doe of old, this was one chief qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that God looked at, if it were but to a Civil Office, between men and men, God requires this, that they ſhould be men fearing God; conſider that counſel that was given by <hi>Jethro</hi> (the Prophet of the Lord) to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 18, 21. <hi>Moreover, thou ſhalt provide out of all the people, able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting covetouſneſs, and place ſuch over them, Rulers of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, of fifties, and tens, and let them judge the people</hi> [to wit, <hi>Iſrael] at all ſeaſons;</hi> (and oh that men would walk after the Laws of this bleſſed people, whoſe Laws were extolled by God above all Laws given to any Nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.8. <hi>What Nation is there</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſo great that hath Statutes, and Judgements ſo righteous, as all this Law which I ſet before you this day</hi>) and the truth is, men of great abilities, that have not the fear of God in their hearts, they are but the greater enemies to the great Deſignes, and Works of the God of heaven.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is a ſweet and bleſſed qualification, that God would have in every one that ſhall bee ſet up for him; ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2, 3. which are the words of the Spirit of the Lord by his ſervant <hi>David,</hi> and this is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168446:9"/>
often inculcated, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſpake by mee, and his word was in my tongue; The God of Iſrael ſaid, the Rock of Iſrael ſpake to mee, hee that ruleth over men, muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this hath been (formerly) much ſet upon the hearts of many, that have been great inſtruments, in the work of God in this Nation, that if they put any in place or office in the Nation, they ſhould bee men fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God; And hath not God made way for ſuch to Rule, having converted ſo many in the Nation.</p>
            <p>But again, conſider, That this glorious qualification of the fear of God, fitted Chriſt for the great work of his Mediatorſhip, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.5. <hi>My Covenant was with him of life and peace, for the fear wherewith he feared mee, and was afraid before my Name:</hi> And in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11.2, 3. which is a Propheſie of Chriſt, it is ſaid, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſhall reſt upon him, the Spirit of wiſdome and underſtanding, the Spirit of counſel and might, the Spirit of knowledge, and of the fear of the Lord:</hi> And doubtleſs this is a moſt bleſſed qualification, to fit a man for any work for God, hee that hath the fear of God in his heart, dares not take the gain of oppreſſion, nor do any thing that is evill, and unrighteous: See it in good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Chap. 5. verſ. 15. ſpeaking of the former Governors, how they oppreſſed and tyrannized over the people; but (ſaith he) <hi>So did not I, becauſe of the Fear of God:</hi> That man that truly fears God, trembles before him, and ſtands in awe of the Great God continually: And thus you ſee how this Fear of God, fits men to ſerve Gods deſigns, in their generation, and therefore this is one leſſon, that God would have men to learn, by his great works in theſe laſt dayes. — But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The other is like to this, <hi>viZ.</hi> To have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168446:9"/>
to the glory of Gods Name; God hath alwayes laid aſide a people that were ſelfiſh and did not minde the advancement of his Name: See <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10, 11. ſaith God, <hi>Who is there even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that would ſhut the door for nought, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do you kindle a fire on my Altar for nought,</hi> [What follows?] <hi>I have no pleaſure in you, ſaith the Lord of Hoaſts, neither will I accept an offering at your hand,</hi> [Why ſo] <hi>For from the riſing of the Sun, to the going down of the ſame, my</hi> NAME <hi>ſhall bee great among the Gentiles, &amp;c.</hi> as if God ſhould ſay, Theſe are not a people, which will bee ſeeking my Name, and my glory, and will do nothing in my ſervice, without a preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, therefore I will ſhake them off, and will not accept an offering from their hand.</p>
            <p>A narrow hearted ſelf-ſeeking man, is unfit to follow God in his great works, for thoſe which will honour God, and give glory to his Name, they muſt truſt God for their daily bread, and above all things minde the hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and advancing of Gods Name, and if they will make it good in earneſt, that they are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt, they muſt be ready to follow the Lord, to the loſs of ALL. For ſaith Chriſt, <hi>He that hates not father and mother, wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, brethren and ſiſters, yea and his own life alſo, he cannot be my diſciple,</hi> Luke 14.26.</p>
            <p>And this is made by God, the diſtinguiſhing difference between thoſe that fear God, and thoſe that fear him not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16. you may there read of a people, that though they gave God ſome outward ſervice, yet they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168446:10"/>
not at the glory of God, but their own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and therefore they cry out, <hi>It is in vain to ſerve God, and what profit is it that wee have kept his Ordinances? &amp;c.</hi> And this is that which a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite looks at, in his ſerving God, even his own profit and advantage: And here I would a little note to you the practiſe of this Nation, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their Miniſtry, that Ordinances which brings no profit to the Miniſters, as namely the great Ordinance of Excommunication, which tends to vindicate the Name of God in the earth, and to diſtinguiſh the precious, from the vile; yet becauſe this Ordinance of caſting out, brings them no profit; how have they caſt it out from among them, whiles other things that bring them in profit, they appear zealous for. And are there not many that ſeem ready to ſerve God, and his cauſe? but if wee look thoroughly upon them, is not their Eye rather upon their own profit, than Gods glory?</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Malachy,</hi> you have alſo men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there made of a people that Feared the Lord, and what they did in that day, verſe 17. of which one thing is, <hi>That they thought upon Gods Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you may ſee what notice God takes of it, and how hee will reward them for it; and this is the diſtinguiſhing difference between the righteous, and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not, verſ. laſt.</p>
            <p>And thus you may ſee how theſe bleſſed qualifications of the Fear of God and Reſpect to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168446:10"/>
his Name, will fit perſons to bee uſed in the great works God hath to do in the laſt dayes; and therefore they are the two great Leſſons he requireth of them.</p>
            <p>I might for further demonſtration of the truth of the point, adde a</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Grounded upon Gods ſeverity againſt perſons for the neglect of theſe things; Gods great controverſie with men all along, hath been upon this ſcore, for not fearing him, and giving glory to his Name, becauſe they did not fear God before all, and honour God above all. See <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 5.24. &amp;c. <hi>Neither ſay they in their heart, Let us now fear the Lord our God,</hi> &amp;c. And at the 29. verſe, ſee what God ſaith, <hi>Shall</hi> I <hi>not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, and ſhall not my ſoul bee avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> So <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. I <hi>will be a ſwift witneſs againſt Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers and Adulterers, and falſe ſwearers, and thoſe that turn aſide the ſtranger from their right, and Fear not mee, ſaith the</hi> LORD <hi>of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the judgements of God in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes ſhall come upon men for this, ſee that forecited text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.7. <hi>Fear God, and give glory to him, for the Hour of his Judgement is come;</hi> and therefore the way to eſcape the juſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God that are coming forth, Is <hi>to fear God, and give glory to his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But ſome may ask, as to the firſt thing God requires, <hi>What this fear of God is, which is ſo often ſpoken of in the Scriptures, as that which God doth ſo much delight in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168446:11"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall at preſent, tender you with ſome deſcription of it, according to that light, and experience, (which I hope I may truly ſay) the Lord hath communicated to me; and you may take it as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſcription,</hi> It is a precious effect of the Spirit of Chriſt, in the heart of a Beleever, whereby (through the diſcovery of the glory of God in his word, and works by Chriſt, and in conſideration of the vaſt diſproportion between God and the creature) he is made to think highly of God in all his Attributes, and to have reſpect unto all his Commandements.</p>
            <p>The definition is ſomething long, but I ſhall prove the particulars to you, and</p>
            <p n="1">1 I ſay, It is a precious effect of the Spirit of Chriſt in the heart of a Beleever, hee is the ſubject of it, and there is none elſe, that hath this fear of God in him, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the wicked, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.18. ſaith, <hi>There is no fear of God before their eyes;</hi> And <hi>David</hi> tells us the like, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.1. they have not this true Son-like fear, natural men are unacquainted with it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That this fear comes by union with Chriſt, and his Spirit, that is the cauſe of it, you may ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11. <hi>Vnite my heart to fear thy name;</hi> this fear of God it comes by vertue of an union with Jeſus Chriſt by faith, for the ſpirit of the fear of the Lord it is given to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2. And he received of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting to ſhed it abroad amongſt his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb facs="tcp:168446:11"/>
and to give it to thoſe that are united to him, and no further then we live in union with Chriſt by faith, can we bee partakers of this gracious frame of ſpirit, to fear the Lord in truth; this is a Leſſon which the Spirit teaches, and therefore it was by the Spirit that <hi>David</hi> cries out, <hi>Come yee children and hearken unto mee, and I will teach you the fear of the Lord,</hi> Pſa. 34.11, and this God hath promiſed to give to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32.40. <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, and they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> But if you ask me, how the Spirit works this in the heart of a Beleever?</p>
            <p n="3">3 I ſay, it is through the diſcovery of the glory of God, in his Word and Works by Chriſt; by the Glory of God I underſtand his Attributes; when <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to ſee Gods Glory, he ſhews him his Attributes, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5, 6. he proclaimed the Name of the Lord; and what is it? why, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth.</hi> This is the diſcovery of Gods Glory, the diſcovery of his Name.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hee begins with his Attribute, that denotes his Soveraignty, and Dominion [The Lord] <hi>Salomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdome;</hi> and [indeed] until a Soul underſtands ſomething of the Soveraignty and Dominion of God over him, hee never comes to make a right uſe of Gods love, and goodneſs, for until the Soul comes to ſee, that God orders all things in Heaven and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168446:12"/>
Earth, and that he is in the hands of the great God, to diſpoſe of him as he will, and that he can deſtroy him, and caſt him to Hell if hee pleaſeth; he cannot finde any ſweetneſs in the tenders of Grace in the Goſpel, nor apply his Soul in reality to them; and therefore I finde that when the Prophets of God, of old time, brought Gods Meſſage to the Sons of men, they uſually ſpake to them as from the Lord, ſaying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord;</hi> you have it ſometimes twice in a verſe, ſetting forth Gods right of Soveraignty over them to whom they delivered their Meſſage; and this is that which is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding needful to bee ſet upon the hearts of the Sons of men, when they come to hear Gods Word, or have any thing to doe in his Works; when the Soul conſiders Gods Soveraignty over him, it cauſes him to ſtand in awe, and fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; and therefore by this you may try your ſelves, whether this fear of God be in you or no; Did the Lord ever ſhew himſelf to you, as the Soveraigne Lord? and make you to lye at his feet as duſt and aſhes? and as clay in the hands of the Potter? for if ever God have wrought this fear in your heart this was your frame, I know many have a notional knowledge of Gods Soveraignty, and are able to write Books of it; but are your hearts really affected with it, ſo as to lye low before the Lord in the apprehenſions of it; I finde it hard in every action, to know this God to be the Soveraigne Lord of all, and that he ruleth in all things, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168446:12"/>
wee are to obey him in thought, word, and deed, and to fear continually before him. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2 There is Gods goodneſs, which is another thing wherein his glory appears, he is the Lord God, merciful, and gracious, and this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former, much conduces to fear him, when the Soul conſiders, that the great God (that made the Heavens, and the Earth, and before whom all Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket) ſhould offer tenders of Grace and Mercy, to be reconciled to ſuch a poor ſinfull Creature; this inclines the heart to hearken to him, and fear before him, knowing this, that <hi>he is the Lord that exerciſeth loving kindneſs, judgement, and righteouſneſs in the earth,</hi> Jerem. 9.24. and that <hi>he is good to all thoſe that fear him, Pſal.</hi> 34.9, 10, 11. this brings the heart over to God indeed, when Gods greatneſs and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is diſplayed before the Soul together, this works up the heart in reality towards God; O how doth <hi>David</hi> admire Gods love, when he conſiders the great Works of God, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.3. <hi>When I conſider the heavens, the works of thy fingers, the Moon, and the Stars which thou haſt made, what is man that thou art mindful of him? and the Son of man that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> and at verſ. 9. <hi>O Lord! how excellent is thy name in all the earth.</hi> he could not but admire, and fear; and fear, and admire Gods great name: — But again,</p>
            <p n="3">3 Let us alſo conſider Gods power, which much conduces in the hand of the Spirit, to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168446:13"/>
work this fear of God, in our hearts, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall finde when God calls upon his people to hearken to him, hee uſeth ſuch kinde of expreſſions as theſe, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, that made the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth, that they cannot bee moved:</hi> And what a ſtrong influence it hath, you may ſee in <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.6.7.10, 12, 13. <hi>There is none like unto thee, Oh Lord, thou art great, and thy Name is great in might, Who would not Fear thee, thou King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Lord is the true God, and the everlaſting King, at his wrath the earth ſhall tremble, and the Nations ſhall not be able to abide his indignation, he hath made the earth by his power, he hath eſtabliſhed the world by his wiſdome, and hath ſtretched forth the heavens by his diſcretion, hee maketh lightning with rain, and bringeth forth the wind out of his treaſures.</hi> Very gloriouſly you ſee the Prophet ſets forth the greatneſs of Gods power, when he comes to declare a meſſage to the people from him.</p>
            <p>So alſo the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in the 40. Chap. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. ſets forth Gods Power, as he hath <hi>meaſured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with a ſpan, and comprehended the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, and weighed the Mountains in ſcales, and the Hills in a ballance; Behold the Nations before him, are but as the drop of a bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the ballance, he taketh up the Iſles as a very little thing, and all Nations before him are as nothing:</hi> And (if that bee not enough) he tells you, <hi>They are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168446:13"/>
counted to him leſs than nothing, and vanity.</hi> So verſ. 22. <hi>It is hee that ſitteth upon the Circle of the earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are as graſhoppers, that ſtretcheth out the Heavens as a curtain, and ſpreadeth them out as a tent to dwell in; That bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Princes to nothing, and maketh the Judges of the earth, as vanity.</hi> Thus you ſee Gods Power which is another of his Attributes; and did but perſons conſider this, who would not fear and tremble before him.</p>
            <p>Again, This fear of God is very much kept in the hearts of the children of God, by eying the Providences of God, and the Works of God (as it is in the deſcription) there is a hand of God in all things that come to paſs in the world: But oh, how many are there that live in the world like Atheiſts, not eying God at all, or elſe perhaps a little at morning and evening (I do not ſpeak againſt this) but their fault is, they do not eye God continually, and therefore if they have got a little of the fear of God upon their hearts after prayer in the morning, they quickly loſe it by going out into the world; and therefore it is of excellent uſe to keep the fear of God alive in the heart, to ſee God in every buſineſs wee are imployed in, with <hi>David, to ſet the Lord alwayes before us;</hi> and you may ſee in that 107. <hi>Pſalm</hi> at large, how excellently the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God are ſet forth, relating to various conditions, to raiſe up the hearts of perſons to fear him, and love him, and praiſe him: Oh then, what's the reaſon that Profeſſors are found
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168446:14"/>
ſo light and vain in their converſations, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not eye God in his Providences, the fear of the Lord is not really in their hearts, and continually before their eyes: if it were, they durſt not bee ſo light and vain in their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as oft-times they are; and ſo alſo the great work of Redemption, is that which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſouls indeed to fear God, as I might abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſhew you; but I muſt haſten, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall paſs on to a</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thing in the deſcription, which (further) relates to the manner how this fear of God is wrought in the heart, and that is by the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the vaſt diſproportion which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the Creature, this is that which tends much to the begetting of the fear of God in the heart, conſider thoſe expreſſions uſed by that Servant of the Lord, <hi>Abraham,</hi> in his drawing nigh to God, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! now I have [taken upon me] to ſpeak unto the Lord, which am but duſt and aſhes;</hi> he did not look upon it as a ſmall matter, to come and pray to God, and ſpeak to God, as too many poor Creatures do, that come to God without that reverence of him in their hearts, and ſuch a geſture in their bodies (both publickly and in their Families, and Cloſets) as becomes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in their drawing nigh to God by prayer, and ſo <hi>Salomon</hi> preſſeth us to reverence, and fear, upon this account, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, nor let thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God, for God is in heaven, and thou art
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168446:14"/>
upon earth, therefore let thy words be few;</hi> and alſo that fore-mentioned place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. ſets forth the diſproportion between God and the creature, <hi>Behold all Nations before him are but as the drop of a bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the ballance, hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth up the Iſles, as a very little thing:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if men, did but conſider, what this great God is, they durſt never walke proudly before him, nor ſpeak proudly againſt him, but would even caſt themſelves upon the ground, as thoſe of old did, when they ſpake to God. And oh! that the conſideration of Gods greatneſs, and that vaſt diſproportion that is between him &amp; us, were more upon our hearts, that ſo we may fear before him continually, and ſo I ſhal come in the</p>
            <p>Fifth place to ſpeak to this fear of God, with reſpect to the nature of it, and the fruits and effects of it, which is ſet forth in the Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription by two things,</p>
            <p>Firſt, A thinking highly of God in all his Attributes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A having reſpect to all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
            <p n="1">1 This fear of God is that whereby the ſoul is made to think highly of God in all his Attributes, it brings a ſoul to thinke highly of Gods Name, which is his Attributes; ſee it in <hi>David,</hi> a man fearing, God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.9, 10. <hi>Holy and Reverent is his Name,</hi> and hee ſubjoyns, <hi>The fear of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This fear of God cauſes the ſoul to have reſpect to all Gods Commandements, the man
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168446:15"/>
that truly fears God, he trembleth at the word of God, hath God ſaid it, it ſhall be done, ſaith the poor humble ſoul, what ever it bee, that God commands, though it bring never ſo much loſs, or ſhame, or ſuffering upon mee, yet if the fear of God be in my heart, I ſhall do it: A ſoul that truly fears God, will endeavour to avoid in thought, word, or deed, what ever offends God, and diſhonours God, as hee would avoid hell: And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The fear of the Lord is to depart from evill,</hi> Prov. 3.7. <hi>Yea to hate evill,</hi> Prov. 8.13. And therefore take a ſoul that hath the fear of God upon his heart, and hee looks upon it as a dreadful thing to ſin againſt God, and to diſhonour God in thought, word, or deed, and therefore as much as may bee, ſuch a ſoul will avoid the occaſions of ſin; you may ſee it in <hi>Agur,</hi> in <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8, 9. ſaith he, <hi>Give me neither poverty, nor riches;</hi> and why? becauſe both thoſe ſtates were dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous temptations to ſin againſt God, and the beſt way to avoid the ſin, is to avoid the temptation: But alas! How many are there in this our day, that are bold and venterous upon temptations, that will ruſh in upon them without fear; How few are there that have this in their prayers to God, <hi>Lord give mee not riches,</hi> but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, how do many run into multitude of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in the world, which ſo takes up their time, and hearts, that they are not fit to ſerve God in their Generation: Not conſidering that of our Saviour, <hi>How hardly ſhall they that have riches,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168446:15"/>
enter into the Kingdome of Heaven?</hi> But the fear of God it teaches the ſoul to avoid the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin, and to abſtain from all appearances of evill, according to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.22. And ſurely, if wee are to pray, <hi>Not to bee led into temptation,</hi> then wee are not to lead our ſelves into temptation; <hi>But firſt to ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you:</hi> And thus the Fear of God teaches to abſtain from what God hath forbidden, and to do what God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, to thinke highly of God in all his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and to have reſpect to all his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</p>
            <p>And thus you have the Deſcription opened, and proved, concerning the fear of God, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to the other duty of giving glory to his name, and therefore ſhall make ſome Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of what hath been ſpoken to our own ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> If it be ſo that the fear of God is one of thoſe great Leſſons God calls upon men to learn by his great Works in the latter dayes, Then let mee exhort, and beſeech you all to learn this bleſſed Leſſon of the Fear of God: It is ſurely a very deſirable thing; It may bee many of you will take it in ſcorn to bee taught this, and bee ready to ſay, What, are wee yet to learn this? Let mee tell you, it is much to bee feared, That many that have made a long pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of God, are yet void of this true filial fear of the Name of God; and therefore to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168446:16"/>
help you a little in it, I ſhall give you but ſome Motives, and ſome Directions, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> 1. Conſider the excellency of the fear of God, it is Prov. 1.7. Pſal. 111.10. <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdome;</hi> and it is good for perſons to obſerve a method and order in what they doe; whiles thou art void of this fear, thou art void of true ſpiritual wiſdome; and therefore <hi>Job</hi> alſo telleth us, <hi>That the fear of the Lord, that is wiſdome, Job</hi> 28. laſt v. And therefore you that are void of ſpiritual wiſdome, and have not the fear of God imprinted upon your hearts, the firſt leſſon you are to learn, is the fear of God, and as you would bee wiſe men, and women, take heed of light and vain ſpirits, for <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>A fool is known by much laughter,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> 2. Conſider that this fear of God, is that which will fit Saints for that glorious ſtate God will bring them into; and by the ſignes of Chriſts coming it ſeems to bee nigh; that diſtreſs that is upon the Nations, ſpeaks ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it: Oh friends, wee are not fit for that familiarity, Saints ſhall then have with God if this fear of God be not upon our hearts. Notions of love will but lead to vanity, and lightneſs, without they bee ballanced by this fear, and therefore to fit, and prepare perſons for Chriſts appearing, and that familiarity, wee ſhall have with him at his coming, this fear of God is abſolutely neceſſary; and therefore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168446:16"/>
thoſe that profeſs to bee moſt inlightned in the truth of Chriſts appearing, and Kingdome, ought much to live in this fear; for you ſhall finde this is the uſe <hi>David</hi> makes of it in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. Having treated of the Kingdome of Chriſt, and the ſubjection of the Nations to him, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with this, verſ. 11. <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motive</hi> 3. Conſider, <hi>The Lord taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them that fear him,</hi> Pſal. 147.11. Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is in ſuch a man, and hee reckons ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Jewels, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18. So when God would triumph of a man, as hee did of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Job,</hi> ſaying, <hi>There is none like him in all the earth, one that [Feareth God] and eſcheweth evill,</hi> Job 1.8. But on the contrary, God takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of light, and proud, and vain profeſſors, they are not worthy of a name in his book by way of Approbation: And when that diſcerning time comes ſpoken of in <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.18. When God makes up his Jewels, then ſhall men diſcern between them that fear God, and thoſe that fear him not; The fear of God, and the love of his Name, are the two great things, by which ſouls ſhall then be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that ſoul that can truſt God for his daily bread here, and for eternal life, and glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and the carnal Profeſſor ſhall then, bee diſtinguiſhed, each from other; and when Saints come to have a more diſcerning ſpirit, they ſhall ſee that none are rightly ſpirited for God, but thoſe which have this Fear of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168446:17"/>
and can look at Gods glory above all things; and the people of God ſhall be much known by this, that they are willing to forbear any thing that tends to their own advantage, when it may diſhonour Gods Name, becauſe they fear God, and love Gods Name; and I beleeve God will put ſuch a difference between <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and their children, between Profeſſors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, that they ſhall bee much diſcerned, and diſcovered by this very thing, the one of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone Gods glory, and the advancement of his Name above all; and the other ſeeking the inriching themſelves, and onely minding their own advancement in the earth, ſuch as theſe, God will manifeſt his diſpleaſure againſt; <hi>But hee taketh pleaſure in them that fear him.</hi> — Again as a</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Motive,</hi> To preſs you to this fear of God, conſider the judgements threatned againſt thoſe that fear him not; for let mee tell you, That notwithſtanding all your outward Profeſſion of the Name of God, yet if this fear of God, bee not in your hearts, you will not bee able to eſcape, the great judgements of the great God againſt thoſe that fear him not, <hi>I will be a ſwift witneſs againſt them that fear not mee, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Mal. 3.5. <hi>But to this man will hee look even to him that trembles at his word,</hi> Iſa. 66.2. And therefore as a</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Motive,</hi> Conſider the many precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes God hath made to them that fear him, <hi>They ſhall bee mine, ſaith the Lord, and when hee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168446:17"/>
makes up his Jewels, he will remember thoſe that fear him;</hi> Yea he hath his book of remembrance for ſuch ſouls, hee will be ſure not to forget them, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>And bleſſed is the man that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alwayes,</hi> Prov. 28.14. And you may finde <hi>David</hi> preſſing to the fear of God upon this account, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34 9, 10. <hi>O fear the Lord, all yee his Saints, for there is no want to them that fear him, the young Lions ſhall lack and ſuffer hunger, but they that fear the Lord ſhall want no good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you may further note, That the great reward that will bee given at the laſt day, is promiſed unto thoſe that have this fear: See it in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. <hi>Hee will reward his ſervants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and thoſe that fear his Name, ſmall and great;</hi> And it is for ſome ſingular goodneſs manifeſted to them that they are called upon to praiſe God, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Praiſe our God all yee his ſervants, and thoſe that fear him both ſmall and great:</hi> And ſo God hath promiſed to hear the prayers, yea to fulfill the deſires of them that fear him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.19. And are not theſe great priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which are promiſed to thoſe that fear God? And therefore let all theſe Motives bee uſefull to work the fear of God where it is not, and to increaſe it where it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But perhaps ſome may ſay, <hi>This fear of God is an excellent thing, but how ſhall wee come by it, wee are not able to plant this plant in our owne ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, This fear of God is a flower that doth not grow in Natures garden; but it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168446:18"/>
is a precious effect of the Spirit of Chriſt in the heart, as I ſhewed you in the Deſcription, but let mee ſay this to you, That ſince the fear of God is ſo excellent a thing, take heed that you do not ſleight it, that you are not like thoſe that in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29. <hi>hated knowledge, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord.</hi> But if you do really deſire to fear God, to help you forward in it, I ſhall give you ſomewhat by way of Direction, which if you obſerve, and practiſe, may bee uſeful by Gods bleſſing to work this fear in your hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 1. Then bee much in the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Sovereignty, and power over thee, and his great Works of Creation and Redemption, and Preſervation, what a God hee is with whom you have to do, and the vaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion that is between you and him; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his abſolute Power, and Authority over you, how you are in his hands, who can do with you what he pleaſes; and as ſoon as thou haſt had any vain thought, or ſpoke any vain word, or done any ſinfull action, hee can, if he pleaſes, ſend thee immediately to Hell, without giving thee leave for one moment longer to breathe in the world; and therefore conſider this, and this may cauſe you to ſtand in awe of him, and to fear to offend him. But again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 2. That which will further conduce to the working of this fear is the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Gods goodneſs, <hi>For there is mercy with him that he may be feared,</hi> Pſal. 130.4. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168446:18"/>
the ſoul cannot have a true filial fear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, but when the ſoul ſeeth the great God in whoſe hands he is, to invite him to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to him, and tendring grace to his ſoul, promiſing him forgiveneſs if hee will but fear him, this melts the heart. Oh! to conſider that the great God of Heaven and Earth, ſhould offer to give himſelf to poor ſouls with all his fulneſs for a ſupply of their wants, if they will but fear him; ſurely this, if beleeved, and conſidered, will cauſe you to love God, and ſerve God, and fear to offend this God, which is ſo good and gracious unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 3. Again, If thou wouldeſt have the fear of God wrought in thy heart, Go to the Word of God, bee much in reading, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and meditating of it, that will ſhew you your duty, and the many arguments to it; and poſſibly hereby God may work this fear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 4. Be alſo much in the obſervation of Gods hand of Providence abroad, and at home, labour to eye God in every diſpenſation that befalls our ſelves or others; ſee God in mercies, and eye God in afflictions when his chaſtiſing hand is upon us, for were our hearts in ſuch a frame, as to eye God continually, it would much work, and increaſe this fear; But then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 5. In the next place, go to God for this fear, cry to him, and pray to him to work, and increaſe this holy fear; This was <hi>Davids</hi> prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11. <hi>Unite my heart to fear thy Name:</hi> And therefore all you that have any bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168446:19"/>
of the Spirit in you, in any meaſure make it your continual requeſt to God, to put this fear in your hearts, and therefore be diligent in the uſe of all theſe means, in order to the begetting and increaſing of this fear, and I ſhall conclude with that of <hi>Salomon,</hi> Prov. 2.4, 5. <hi>If thou ſeekeſt her as ſilver, and ſearcheſt for her as for bid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, then ſhalt thou underſtand the fear of the Lord, and finde the knowledge of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But perhaps ſome tender hearts that have the fear of God, in truth, may bee apt to ſay, I much queſtion, whither yet I have the fear of God in my heart in truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now, as this queſtion may proceed from ſome tender hearts, and conſcientious ſouls that have the fear of God in them, I would apply that word in <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> which I have found much comfort in, to my own ſoul, and would commend it unto you, it is in the firſt of <hi>Nehem.</hi> the laſt verſe, <hi>Let now thy ear be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive unto thy Servant, that [deſires] to fear thy name; Nehemiah</hi> a good man, yet when hee comes before the Lord, he durſt not own that he feared him, but his deſires was that he might fear him; and therefore if thou canſt not take the comfort of ſuch Promiſes as are made to thoſe that fear the Lord, yet if thou haſt deſire in thy ſoul to fear him, and preſſeſt after this fear of God, thou maiſt take comfort in the ſaying of this good man <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who was one that had a deſire to fear Gods name.</p>
            <p>But let none deceive himſelf with this, for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168446:19"/>
every common Proteſtant will ſay that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to fear God; but if you deſire it in truth, your ſouls will bee much in ſeeking to God for it, and endeavouring after it, and to ſuch ſouls, I would commend that word in <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, and they ſhall not depart from mee;</hi> which promiſe belongs not to the <hi>Jews</hi> onely, but to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo, who are fellow heirs with them, and partakers of the promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. and therefore apply this promiſe to thy ſoul: It may bee thou haſt a light vain ſpirit, and art apt to forget what thou heareſt, and to turn aſide and depart from God; but God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to put his fear into the hearts of his people; and then (ſaith hee) <hi>They ſhall never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fear of God, it will keep a ſoul from a backſliding ſpirit, and therefore if thou wouldeſt have this fear, look upon this promiſe, and pray over it, as <hi>David</hi> did upon a word of God, as you may ſee, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.25. <hi>For thou, Oh my God, haſt told thy ſervant, that thou wilt build him an houſe, therefore thy ſervant hath found in his heart to pray before thee.</hi> And if wee would have our hearts brought into a praying frame, wee muſt faſten upon the promiſes, and ſee what promiſes God hath made, that ſuit our condition, and plead the promiſe with him; and when you finde free promiſes made through Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worth on merit in the creature.</p>
            <p>Oh come to God by faith in thoſe promiſes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168446:20"/>
and plead them with God; ask God what his wayes are, wherein hee will make good his promiſes, and wait upon him therein, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly as to the matter in hand concerning the feare of God, ſay as <hi>David</hi> did in another caſe, <hi>Lord thou haſt promiſed to put thy fear into my heart, and therefore thy ſervant hath found in his heart to pray unto thee; Good Lord, let it bee accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy word: Wilt thou put thy fear in my heart, that I may never depart from thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let mee beſeech you, to receive this Exhortation, as in the fear of God; and apply your hearts with all your might, to learn this great Goſpel Leſſon of the Feare of God. Conſider that Promiſe and Propheſie in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3. laſt. where it is ſaid of a people, <hi>They ſhall fear the Lord and his goodneſs in the latter dayes:</hi> And oh that the fear of the Lord may reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every heart that hears before him this day: Surely his judgements call upon us to fear him, and his mercies call upon us to fear him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Onely fear the Lord and ſerve him, in truth, and with a perfect heart, for conſider how great things hee hath done for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that you might now go away with ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits, weighty ſpirits (for God weigheth the ſpirits) that you may bee no more light, and vain, but may make this your firſt prayer to God, how you may moſt honour God, and bring glory to him in your Generation.</p>
            <trailer>But ſo much for this time.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
